Finding Aid for Computing Center (University of Michigan) publications, 1965-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Computing Center (University of Michigan) publications, 1965-1999 1965-1999
University of Michigan. Computing Center.
18 linear feet
0351 Bimu 2
Established in 1959 to operate academic computing facility and provide computing services for faculty and students. Developed Michigan Terminal System (MTS) operating system and other software for mainframe computers. Merged into University of Michigan Information Technology Division in 1985. Publications include technical manuals and reports on U-M developed software and network design, newsletters, and general reports on computing at the university.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Publications are received periodically from the unit (donor # 7873 ). 7873
Publications are open for research.
For historical note, please consult manuscripts finding aid for University of Michigan Computing Center Records.
The Computing Center Publications include brochures and pamphlets, bulletins and course catalogs including "Non-Credit Computing Courses on Campus," manuals including "Info Tech Guide" and "Welcome to Computing at the University of Michigan", newsletters, technical reports, and general reports, such as "Resources and Plans of the University of Michigan with Regard to the Establishment of Data Processing and Computer Center. The manuals and technical reports include documentation the Michigan Terminal System (MTS, U-M's pioneering time-sharing system for the IBM 360 class of computers, the Michigan Algorithm Decoder (MAD operating system) and the University of Michigan Executive System (UMES.) The Computing Center Publications are divided into three series: Unit Publications, Sub-Unit Publications, and Technical Memos and Technical Reports.
Subjects:
University of Michigan. Computing Center.; Computers.; Michigan Terminal System.; Non-credit computing courses on campus.; InfoTech guide.; Welcome to computing at the University of Michigan.; Resources and plans of the University of Michigan with regard to the establishment of data processing and Computer Center.
Genre Terms:
Bulletins.; Manuals.; Newsletters.; Reports.
- Unit Publications
  In the Unit Publications series, there are several brochures about the Computing Center. They include a brochure titled The University of Michigan Computing Center written in 1971 for the building dedication and a brief introduction to the Computing Center entitled Welcome to the University of Michigan Computing Center.
  Also included are the bulletins, or course catalogs Non-Credit Computing Courses on Campus, which describe classes offered by the Computing Center to students, faculty, and staff. These courses range from introductory classes for the computer novice to advanced computer sessions for the experienced user.
  - Articles about the Computing Center 1964-1976
  - Bibliographies (Box 1)
    - CCPublications, June 1980 (Box 1)
  - Brochures
    - General 1967-1984 (Box 1)
    - Instructional Computing in the Sites: Opportunities for U-M Faculty, 1995 (Box 1)
    - The University of Michigan Computing Center, 1971 (Box 1)
    - Welcome to the University of Michigan Computing Center, 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - Bulletins (Course Catalogs)
    - Non-Credit Computing Courses on Campus, 1985-1990, 3 folders (Box 1)
      (continues in Information Technology Division Publications)
  - Catalogs
    - List and Index of Some Statistical Programs Available at the University of Michigan 360/67 Under MTS, January 1970 (Box 1)
  - Directories
    - Computing Center Reference List, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Manuals
    The bulk of this series is composed of the serial manual Computing Center Memos. CCMemos were published irregularly from 1967 through 1987, numbered 2 through 924, though not necessarily in chronological order. Numbers 2 through 599 are general memos about various software and hardware; the 600 series are the Consultant's Notes series--short memos for beginning to intermediate users; the 800 series covers issues relating to the Xerox 9700 mainframe, text processing, and typesetting; and the 900 series covers microcomputers. There was no 700 series. Lists and subject indices for the CCMemos can be found in Box 4, following the memos themselves.
    The manuals Computing Resources on Campus and Quicknotes, describe the computing environment at the University of Michigan, as well as detailed instructions on how to sign on, how to get help when needed, and the proper use policy. Other manuals instruct the user about specific programs and software including UM/TRAC, XPL and Polygraphics.
    - Computing Center Memos
      (precedes Reference series)
      - nos. 2-198 1967-1971, 10 folders (Box 1)
      - nos. 199-346 1971-1977, 15 folders (Box 2)
      - nos. 347-470 1977-1987, 15 folders (Box 3)
      - nos. 471-924 1985-1988, 9 folders (Box 4)
      - List of All CCMemos, July 1970-August 1973 (Box 4)
      - List and Subject Index of CCMemos, March 1974-March 1979 (Box 4)
      - List of CCMemos, March 1980-April 1988 (Box 4)
    - Computing Resources on Campus, 1989-1990 (Box 4)
    - A Digital Plotting System for Producing Device-Independent Plot Descriptions--Draft, by E.J. Fronczak, August 1968 (Box 4)
    - The Display File Routines User's Guide, by Richard P. Wagman
      - December 1970 (Box 4)
      - August 1972 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1967-1969 (Box 4)
    - Polygraphics User's Manual, undated (Box 4)
    - Quicknotes
      (continues in ITD Publications under User Services)
      - 1985 (Box 4)
      - 1986 (Box 4)
      - 1987 (+ index) (Box 4)
      - 1988 (+ index) (Box 4)
    - Reference
      (supersedes Computing Center Memos, continues in ITD Publications)
      - nos. R1021-R1048 1989-1991 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan Computing Center: Organization, System Architecture and Hardware Facilities, circa 1986 (Box 4)
    - The University of Michigan Digital Plotting System
      - undated (+ revisions) (Box 4)
      - September 1966 (Box 4)
      - September 1966 (errata) (Box 4)
      - March 1967 (Box 4)
    - UM/TRAC: The Text Reckoning and Compiling Language at the University of Michigan, April 1967 (Box 4)
    - XPL User's Guide, undated (Box 4)
  - Maps
    - Map of U-M Computing Services, undated (Box 4)
  - Newsletters
    There is a long run of newsletters under three titles Computing Center News, Computing Center Newsletter, and U-M Computing News, covering the period from 1971 to 1991. Subject indices for the Computing Center Newsletter may be found in front of the appropriate folder of volumes 2 through 10. U-M Computing News combined with two other ITD publications-- UIS (previously OAS) Newsletter and Communication Lines-- to form The Information Technology Digest in 1992. The Information Technology Digest will be found in the Information Technology Division record group.
    - Computing Center News
      - nos. 1-308 1967-1971, 5 folders (Box 4)
      - Indexes 1969-1971 (Box 4)
    - Computing Center Newsletter, 1971-1986, 16 folders (Box 5)
    - Get Info, 1989 (Box 5)
    - Micro Digest, 1985 (Box 5)
    - U-M Computing News, 1986-1987, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - U-M Computing News, 1988-1991, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - Programs
    - Twentieth Anniversary Celebration, 1979 (Box 6)
  - Proposals
    - Resources and Plans of the University of Michigan with Regard to the Establishment of Data Processing and Computer Center, 1957, 2 copies (Box 6)
    - The University of Michigan Computing Center Three-Year Plan: 1982-1985, September 1982 (Box 6)
  - Surveys
    - Mini/Micro Cross Support Survey, undated (Box 6)
- Sub-Unit Publications
  The Sub-Unit Publications series contains materials published by the Merit Computer Network, two of the University's operating systems--the Michigan Terminal System (MTS) and the University of Michigan Executive System (UMES)--and the University of Michigan Computing Center Lecture Series.
  - Merit Computer Network
    The bulk of the Merit Computer Network subseries is composed of manuals for users of the network, such as the Merit Computer Network User's Guide from 1973 and 1975, and the serial manual, User's Memo, which was published in 1976 and 1977. A Theoretical Study of Store-and-Forward Message Switching in the Merit Computer Network, from June of 1975, may be found under the heading of Reports.
    Merit published a newsletter Merit Network News, beginning in 1986, which was bound with U-M Computing News. The researcher will find them in the Unit Publications series, under Newsletters. There were four issues each year. The newsletter's name was changed in 1990 to Michnet News, and continued to be bound with U-M Computing News until the next year. When U-M Computing News was replaced by ITD Digest in 1991, Michnet News followed, and volumes 7 and 8 may be found in the Information Technology Division record group, in ITD Digest volumes 1 and 2.
    - Brochures undated (Box 6)
    - Manuals
      - Educational Computing at the University of Michigan: A Survey of Activities and Resources, 1973-1974, September 1974 (Box 6)
      - Facilities and Resources Available Via the Merit Host Computing Centers, May 1973 (Box 6)
      - Link Editor User's Guide, August 1970 (Box 6)
      - The MAL [Merit Assembly Language] User's Guide, August 1970 (Box 6)
      - Merit Computer Network User's Guide
        - April 1973 (Box 6)
        - August 1975 (Box 6)
      - User's Memo, nos. 4-15, June 1976-July 1977 (Box 6)
        (continues in ITD Publications, under Merit Computer Network)
    - Reports
      - A Theoretical Study of Store-and-Forward Message Switching in the Merit Computer Network, June 1975 (Box 6)
  - Michigan Terminal System (MTS)
    The Michigan Terminal System (MTS) subseries is mainly composed of manuals, as well, including four versions of the MTS Operators Manual, the User Guide Series (which changed to the MTS User Guide Series after 1981), and several others which describe either the basic procedures of MTS, or the details of programs run on the system, such as FORTRAN, SNOBOL and Taxir. The manual series MTS: The Michigan Terminal System, was published from 1967 through 1991, in volumes 1 through 23, which was updated and reissued irregularly, and occasionally changed names. For instance, eleven editions of Volume 1 were published, under the name Volume 1 in 1967, Volume 1: MTS and the Computing Center in 1971 and 1973, and Volume 1: The Michigan Terminal System from 1976 through 1991.
    The MTS subseries also contains an almost complete run of the MTS Newsletter, which was published from 1971 through 1987, every other month in the beginning, then later, three or four times a year.
    - Manuals
      - Data Concentrator Operations, February 1968 (Box 6)
      - Fundamental Use of the MTS (Including Simple MTS BASIC), by Thomas J. Schriber, 1981 (Box 6)
      - Introduction to SNOBOL-IV, February 1970 (Box 6)
      - Introduction to the Computing Center and to MTS, by L.K. Flanigan, September 1969 (Box 6)
      - MTS Basic Skills--Lecture/Demonstration, August 1988 (Box 6)
      - MTS Message Manual, July 1977 (Box 6)
      - MTS Operators Manual (Box 7)
        - April 1980, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - August 1981, 2 folders (Box 7)
        - September 1981 (Box 7)
        - October 1981, 2 folders (Box 7)
      - MTS Reference Summary, 1977-1989 (Box 7)
      - MTS: The Michigan Terminal System
        (continues in Reference series in ITD Publications)
        - Volume 1, December 1967 (Box 7)
        - Volume 1: MTS and the Computing Center
          - February 1971, 2 folders (Box 7)
          - January 1973 (Box 7)
        - Volume 1: The Michigan Terminal System
          - April 1976, 2 folders (Box 7)
          - October 1978, 2 folders (Box 7)
          - December 1979, 2 folders (Box 7)
          - February 1983, 2 folders (Box 8)
          - January 1984, 2 folders (Box 8)
          - May 1984 (Box 8)
          - November 1988 (Box 8)
          - November 1991 (Box 8)
        - Volume 2, December 1967 (Box 8)
        - Volume 2: Public File Descriptions
          - November 1969 (Box 8)
          - April 1971, 2 folders (Box 8)
          - December 1972 (Box 8)
          - January 1975 (Box 8)
          - December 1978, 2 folders (Box 8)
          - April 1982, 2 folders (Box 9)
          - May 1986 (Update 6) (Box 9)
          - January 1987 (Box 9)
        - Volume 3: Subroutine and Macro Descriptions
          - June 1970, 2 folders (Box 9)
          - May 1973 (Box 9)
        - Volume 3: System Subroutine Descriptions
          - October 1976, 2 folders (Box 9)
          - February 1983, 2 folders (Box 9)
          - January 1984 (Update 3) (Box 9)
          - September 1984 (Update 4) (Box 9)
          - April 1985 (Update 5) (Box 9)
          - September 1985 (Update 6) (Box 9)
          - July 1987 (Update 7) (Box 9)
        - Volume 4: Terminals and Tapes
          - September 1972 (Box 9)
          - August 1974 (Box 9)
          - November 1980, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Volume 4: Terminals and Networks in MTS, March 1984 (Box 10)
        - Volume 5: System Services
          - December 1971 (Box 10)
          - March 1974 (Box 10)
          - June 1976 (Box 10)
          - April 1980 (Box 10)
          - September 1985 (Box 10)
        - Volume 6: FORTRAN in MTS
          - March 1976, 2 folders (Box 10)
          - December 1978, 2 folders (Box 10)
          - February 1988, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Volume 7: PL/I in MTS
          - July 1977 (Box 10)
          - September 1985 (Box 10)
        - Volume 9: SNOBOL in MTS
          - March 1969 (Box 10)
          - May 1984 (Box 10)
        - Volume 10: BASIC in MTS
          - August 1971 (Box 11)
          - September 1974 (Box 11)
          - December 1980 (Box 11)
        - Volume 11: Plot Description System
          - April 1971 (Box 11)
          - April 1985 (Box 11)
        - Volume 12: PIL/2 in MTS, December 1974 (Box 11)
        - Volume 13: Data Concentrator User's Guide, August 1973 (Box 11)
        - Volume 13: The Symbolic Debugging System, September 1985 (Box 11)
        - Volume 14: 360/370 Assemblers in MTS
          - June 1976 (Box 11)
          - August 1978 (Box 11)
          - May 1983 (Box 11)
          - September 1986 (Update 1) (Box 11)
        - Volume 15: FORMAT and TEXT360, March 1988 (Box 11)
        - Volume 16: ALGOL W in MTS
          - August 1978 (Box 11)
          - September 1980, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Volume 17: Integrated Graphics System, September 1984 (Box 11)
        - Volume 18: MTS File Editor
          - September 1982 (Box 12)
          - August 1985 (Box 12)
          - February 1988 (Box 12)
        - Volume 19: Tapes and Floppy Disks
          - February 1983 (Box 12)
          - November 1986 (Box 12)
          - October 1989 (Box 12)
        - Volume 20: PASCAL in MTS, December 1985 (Box 12)
        - Volume 21: MTS Command Extensions and Macros, April 1986 (Box 12)
        - Volume 23: Messaging and Conferencing in MTS
          - March 1987 (Box 12)
          - August 1988 (Box 12)
          - February 1991 (Box 12)
      - MTS: UMMPS Terminal System
        - March 1967 (Box 12)
        - June 1967 (Box 12)
      - MTS User Guide Series
        (supersedes User Guide Series, precedes Tutorial series)
        - Getting connected--Introduction to Terminals and Microcomputers
          - March 1986 (Box 12)
          - September 1987 (Box 12)
        - Getting it on tape--Introduction to Magnetic Tapes
          - September 1986 (Box 12)
          - January 1990 (Box 12)
        - Getting it right--Introduction to MTS File Editor, June 1986 (Box 12)
        - Getting organized--Introduction to Database Management Systems on MTS, March 1986 (Box 12)
        - Getting started--Introduction to MTS, August 1987 (Box 13)
        - Getting the bugs out--An Introduction to Programming and Debugging in MTS, January 1986 (Box 13)
      - PLI: Batch Compilation of MTS PL/I Source Programs, circa 1968 (Box 13)
      - SDS Reference Manual, circa 1968 (Box 13)
      - The Taxir Primer, by R.C. Brill
        - May 1974 (Box 13)
        - February 1983 (Box 13)
      - TEXTFORM Reference Manual, January 1986 (Box 13)
      - Tutorial, no. T7007 1989 (Box 13)
        (continues in ITD Publications)
      - Usage of Device Commands at MTS Terminals, May 1968 (Box 13)
      - User Guide Series
        (precedes MTS User Guide Series)
        - Introduction to FORMAT
          - June 1977 (Box 13)
          - October 1980 (Box 13)
        - Introduction to Magnetic Tapes, September 1979 (Box 13)
        - Introduction to MTS
          - September 1978 (Box 13)
          - September 1980 (Box 13)
      - User Guide Series
        - Introduction to Terminals
          - November 1977 (Box 13)
          - February 1981 (Box 13)
        - Introduction to the Computing Center
          - circa 1970 (draft) (Box 13)
          - September 1977 (Box 13)
          - September 1978 (Box 13)
          - September 1979 (Box 13)
          - September 1980 (Box 13)
          - September 1981 (Box 13)
      - Using the SCORS* Package in MTS, March 1968 (Box 13)
      - Volume 99 (Internals Documentation), 1978 (Box 13)
    - Newsletters
      - MTS Newsletter
        - nos. 1-9 1971-1972 (Box 13)
        - nos. 10-51 1973-1978 (Box 14)
        - nos. 52-84 1979-1987 (Box 15)
  - Taxir User's Group
    - Newspapers
      - TUG News, 1974 (Box 15)
  - University of Michigan Computing Center Lecture Series
    The University of Michigan Computing Center Lecture Series subseries contains a syllabus from around 1979, though no lectures.
    - Syllabi circa 1979 (Box 16)
  - University of Michigan Executive System (UMES)
    The University of Michigan Executive System (UMES) subseries contains manuals detailing procedures and computer languages used with the operating system, including several editions of University of Michigan Executive System for the IBM 7090 Computer, a manual that was produced from 1963 through 1966.
    - Manuals
      - 709 System, August 1961 (Box 16)
      - 7090 Teacher Package, March 1967 (Box 16)
      - Input-Output Subroutines, January 1960 (Box 16)
      - MAD Double Precision and Complex Define Packages, circa 1966 (Box 16)
      - Michigan Executive System Subroutines
        - October 1960 (Box 16)
        - 1962 (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous circa 1960 (Box 16)
      - SAP--The SHARE Assembly Program, February 1960 (Box 16)
      - The System Loader, February 1960 (Box 16)
      - UMAP (University of Michigan Assembly Program), September 1962 (Box 16)
      - UMAP Macros, September 1962 (Box 16)
      - The University of Michigan Executive System
        - January 1960 (Box 16)
        - February 1961 (Box 16)
        - September 1962 (Box 16)
      - University of Michigan Executive System for the IBM 7090 Computer
        - September 1963, 2 folders (Box 16)
        - September 1964, 2 folders (Box 16)
        - September 1965
          - Volume 1 (Box 16)
          - Volume 2 (Box 16)
          - Volume 3 (Box 16)
        - September 1966
          - Volume 1 (Box 16)
          - Volume 2 (Box 16)
- Technical Memos
  Technical Memos and Technical Reports include serially issued technical memos and reports authored by Computing Center staff and university faculty members from 1966 to 1970. Many relate to specific computing programs such as MAD and MTS.
  - No. 1. MAD/I: Preliminary Draft,Galler 1966 (Box 17)
  - No. 2. Comparative Evaluation of Digital Equipment Corporation's 340 and 330 Display Controls, Lundstrom and Westervelt 1966 (Box 17)
  - No. 3. DEC 338 Light Pen Sense Indicator, Lundstrom 1966 (Box 17)
  - No. 4. PDP-8/103A Dataphone Interface, Lundstrom 1966 (Box 17)
  - No. 5. RAMP: A PDP-8 Multiprogramming System for Real-Time Device Control, Mills 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 6. PDP-8/338 Executive System, Frantz 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 7. Use of DDT with "Interrupts On" Programs, Brender 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 8. PDP-8 Simulator, Lundstrom and Callan 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 9. Engineering Design Report: PDP-8/CRO1B Card Reader Interface, Lundstrom 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 10. Engineering Design Report: PDP-7/Modified 338 Display Interface, Lundstrom 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 11. I/O Extensions to RAMP, Mills 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 12. PDP-8 Assembler, Powers 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 13. System/360 Interface Engineering Report, Mills 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 14. Dexeditor, Burkhalter 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 15. A 201A Data Communication Adapter for the PDP-8: Preliminary Engineering Design Report, Wood 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 16. PDP-8 to 103A Dataphone and/or Online Teletype Interface, Burkhalter, Jr. 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 17. PDP-8 Program Relocation Concepts and Facilities, Mills and Powers 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 18. The MTS Data Collection Facility, Pinkerton 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 19. A Cyclic Check Computer for Error Detection, Burkhalter 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 20. An Assembly Language System for DEC Minicomputers, Powers, Mills and Laurance 1969 (Box 17)
  - No. 21. Portaterm Software, Powers 1969 (Box 17)
  - No. 22. The Electrowriter as a Computer I/O Device, McCreery, Estry and Osterwisch 1969 (Box 17)
  - No. 23. The DF Routines User's Guide, Cocanower 1969 (Box 17)
  - No. 24. RAMP Architecture in a Utility Calculator System, Mills 1969 (Box 17)
  - No. 25. Modifications to the SEL Executive System, Jackson and Blinn 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 26. The Discrete, Logical Design, Simulation System, Guskin and Dingwall 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 27. MOMS: Michigan's Own Mathematical System, edited by Taylor 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 28. CAMA: Define Problem Command, Goodrich 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 29. The CAMA Data Structure, Julyk and Wolf 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 30. The CAMA Operating System, Julyk 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 31. Defaults and Block Structure in the MAD/I Language, Springer 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 32. An Example Definitional Facility in MAD/I, Srodawa 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 33. CAMA (Computer-Aide Mathematical Analysis): A General Description, Wolf 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 34. Graphics RAMP User's Manual, Gerstenberger and Taylor 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 35. The CAMA Macro Processor, Dingwall, Julyk and Wolf 1970 (Box 17)
  - No. 36. The CAMA Interpreter, Dingwall, Julyk and Wolf 1970 (Box 17)
- Technical Reports
  - No. 1. Entropy and the Complexity of Graphs, Mowshowitz 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 2. The Engineering Assistant: Design of a Symbol Manipulation System, Sibley 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 3. Description of a Set-Theoretic Data Structure, Childs 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 4. Program Behavior and Control in Virtual Storage Computer Systems, Pinkerton 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 5. TRAMP: A Relational Memory with an Associative Base, Ash and Sibley 1967 (Box 17)
  - No. 6. Feasibility of a Set-Theoretic Data Structure: A General Structure Based on a Reconstituted Definition of a Relation, Childs 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 7. The Syntactic Structure of MAD/1, Mills 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 8. The Data Concentrator, Mills 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 9. Man-Computer Synergism for Decision Making in the System Design Process, Allan III 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 10. LOCOSS: A Multiprogramming Monitor for the DEC PDP-7, Frantz, Brender and Foy, Jr. 1968 (Box 17)
  - No. 11. Specialized System Software for Interacting DEC PDP-7 and IBM 1800 Computers, Brender, Frantz, Foy, Jr. and Schunior, 1968 (Box 18)
  - No. 12. Flexible, High-Speed Interface Between IBM 1800 and DEC PDP-7 Computers, Brender and Foy, Jr., 1968 (Box 18)
  - No. 13. Network Models for the Conversational Design of Stochastic Service Systems, Wallace and Irani 1968 (Box 18)
  - No. 14. A System for the Solution of Simple Stochastic Networks, Irani and Wallace 1969 (Box 18)
  - No. 15. An Executive System for a DEC 339 Computer Display Terminal, Jackson 1968 (Box 18)